Guide to the Paul C. Daniels Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Paul C. Daniels Papers
1903-1988
MS 1903
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
4.05
(7 boxes)
The papers comprise correspondence; subject and research files; writings and speeches; and photographs documenting the personal life and professional career of Paul Daniels as a Foreign Service officer and diplomat.
Daniels, Paul C. (Paul Clement), 1903-1986
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The materials were the gift of Jean Daniels Portell, 2007.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
Paul Clement Daniels was born in Buffalo, New York, on October 26, 1903. He graduated from Yale in 1924 with a degree in philosophy. After a brief time teaching, Daniels entered the Foreign Service in July 1927, serving as chairman of the Inter-American Coffee Board, 1941-1943; counselor of the Embassy, Bogota, Colombia, 1943-1945; Rio de Janeiro, Brazil, 1945-1947; ambassador to Honduras, 1947; director for American Republic Affairs, 1947-1949; and delegate to the Ninth International Conference of American States, Bogota, 1948; ambassador to the Council of the Organization of American States, 1948-1950; and ambassador to Ecuador, 1951-1953. He retired in 1953 but served as a special advisor on Antarctica for the United States Department of State, 1957-1959. Daniels died in 1986.
Scope and Contents
The papers comprise correspondence; subject and research files; writings and speeches; and photographs documenting the personal life and professional career of Paul Daniels as a Foreign Service officer and diplomat.
Arrangement
The materials are arranged chronologically by topic.
Antarctic Treaty system; Daniels, Paul C. (Paul Clement), 1903-1986; Inter-American Coffee Board; United States. Foreign Service
- Biographical information
  - Infancy, 1903-1914 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
  - "In the Clutches of the Scarlet Dragon", circa 1914 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Scope and Contents
    Illustrated childhood story written with David Cavers.
  - Yale photographs from the album of John Alden (Pete) Daniels, Class of 1919, 1916-1917 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Yale materials, 1920-1924 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Class of 1924 photographs, freshman and senior year, 1921, 1924 (Box 7)
  - First summer at sea, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Riverdale Country School, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Passports, 1928-1964 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Yale Class of 1924 Tenth Reunion, 1934 June (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Clippings, 1954-1955 (Box 1, Folder 10-11)
  - Republican Party/Eisenhower fundraising poster, Lakeville, 1956 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Clippings and photographs, 1956-1959 (Box 1, Folder 12-13)
  - San Diego photographs, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Yale Class of 1924 35th reunion photograph, 1959 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Clippings, 1960-1961 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Vassar, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Clippings and correspondence concerning commencement address.
  - Correspondence and clippings, 1962-1970 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Yale Class of 1924 45th and 60th reunions, 1969, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Oral history interview, Harry S. Truman Library, transcript, 1978 September (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Diplomatic Service and Foreign Travel
  - European trip, 1923 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - France, 1924 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Letters of recommendation for French school and Foreign Service, 1924-1926 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Washington, 1926-1928 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - State Department instructions, correspondence, etc., 1927-1969 (Box 2, Folder 7-8)
  - Photographic postcards, 1928-1947 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Valparaiso general, 1928 April-1929 June (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Cali and Buenaventura, 1929 June-1930 July (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - La Paz and Managua, 1930-1954 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Coffee Association scrapbook honoring Paul C. Daniels, 1941-1943 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Coffee publications, 1941-1943, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
  - Autographed photographs of Arthur Bliss Lane, Cornelia B. Lane, and Enrico Dutka, 1944, 1949 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Sumner Welles correspondence, 1947-1955 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Photographs of Daniels and other dignitaries, circa 1948-1959 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Carta de la Organizacion de los Estados Americanos, 1948 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Primera Aplicacion del Tratado Interamericano de Asistencia Reciproca, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Jamison, Edward A., Keeping Peace in the Caribbean Area, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence concerning Drew Pearson, 1952-1953 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Committee for Cultural Action, 1962-1963 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Antarctica and Antarctic Treaty
  - Antarctica treaty, 1958-1960 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Official papers pertaining to conference and treaty, 1958-1964 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Antarctic Treaty Conference photographs, 1959 November 23 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Hanessian, John, The Antarctic Treaty 1959, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Daniels, Paul C., "The Antarctic Treaty," Bulletin of the Atomic Scientists, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Antarctican Society
    - 1963-1982 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Ruth Siple and Paul Dalrymple, 1987-1988 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - General background information on Antarctica, 1945-1970 (Box 4, Folder 1-2)
  - National Science Foundation consultant, Antarctic
    - 1959-1970 (Box 4, Folder 3-4)
    - Administrative, 1964-1971 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Photographs and clippings, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1971-1984 (Box 4, Folder 7-9)
- Miscellaneous correspondence, 1937-1971 (Box 4, Folder 10-11)
- Writings and speeches
  - Compositions, 1937-1954 (Box 5, Folder 1-2)
  - Speeches, 1948-1966 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Hartford Courant
    - General, 1955-1959 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Editorials, 1955-1956 (Box 5, Folder 5-7)
  - Lecturer, 1954-1964 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    Correspondence concerning lectures and panel discussions.
  - Pearson and Eaton, Inc. lecture management correspondence, 1954-1956 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Book reviews, 1971-1972 (Box 5, Folder 10)